死ぬ？
Die?!
How come becoming one
with nature means dying?
自然と一体になることが
どうして死ぬことなんだってばよ。
ガマ吉 死ねとはなんじゃ 死ねとは。
Gamakichi, what's with the dying?!
Don't make such weird analogies!
変な例えを出すな！
だって…。
But...
安心せえ 実際に ナルトちゃんが
死ぬわけじゃありゃへん。
Relax. You're not actually
going to die, Naruto-boy.
なら いったい？
Then what?
Just wait 'til I'm finished...
ワシの話を最後まで聞け。
順を追って 話すけんのう。
I'll explain it stepwise.
Absorbing Nature Energy...
(フカサク)自然エネルギーを
己に取り込むというのは➡
それを感じとり
己に吸い寄せることが➡
It means the ability to
sense it around you
and draw it into yourself.
できるようになる
ということじゃ。
更に 自然と一体になることで➡
In addition,
by becoming one with nature,
自然エネルギーの身体への出入りを➡
you also gain full control
over the Nature Energy
自由に
コントロールできるようにもなる。
entering and leaving your body.
修業の内容を
具体的に言うとじゃな。
Practically speaking,
in terms of your training...
Yeah, yeah?
うん うん！
Sit still.
動くな。
は？
Huh?
動かんということじゃ。
It means sit still!
自然エネルギーは
動物としての流れを止め➡
When you cease your flow
of animal instincts
and harmonize with
the flow of nature,
自然の流れと調和したときに➡
you will be able to sense
Nature Energy for the first time.
初めて感じとることができる。
つまり 動かなきゃいいのか？
So I just stay still?
なんか簡単そうだな それ。
That seems easy enough.
ナルト お前 わかっとらんのう。
Naruto, you really don't get it, do you?
動物にとって 動かずにいることが
いちばんつらいんじゃ。
For animals, not moving is
the hardest thing to do.
跳んだり走ったり
力入れてチャクラ練ったり➡
Jumping, running, molding chakra
with all my strength...
そんな修業ならやったけど➡
I've done those sorts of training.
動くなって
いまいち ピンとこない修業だな。
But staying still? I don't quite get it.
でも それで 自然エネルギーってのが
取り込めるんだな。
But that's how you take
in Nature Energy, right?
いきなりは ムリじゃ。
時間がかかる修業じゃけんのう。
It's impossible to do it right away.
This training requires time,
これは かなり難度高めじゃ。
since the degree of difficulty
is very high.
そんなに時間がかかんのかよ。
It's gonna take that long?!
甘ったれるな ナルトちゃん。
Don't take it so lightly, Naruto-boy!
敵は輪廻眼
六道仙人の力を持つ ペイン。
Our enemy is Pain,
who possesses the Rinnegan...
The power of the
Sage of the Six Paths.
自来也ちゃんを倒した強敵じゃ。
A powerful enemy
who killed Jiraiya-boy.
そんな心構えじゃ
勝てりゃせんぞ！
With that kind of attitude,
you can't possibly win!
そんなことは わかってる！
I know all that!
Pain is the leader of the Akatsuki,
who are after Tailed Beasts.
ペインは 尾獣を狙う暁のリーダー。
すぐにでも
オレのところへやってくる。
They could come for me
at any moment.
あまり時間をかけてらんねえんだ。
I don't have much time to waste.
まあ とはいっても➡
Well, it's not as though
there isn't a better way...
もっと いい方法が
ないこともないがのう。
あんのかよ。
なら それで教えてくれよ。
There is?!
Then teach me that!
この後ろの滝。
This waterfall behind me...
妙木山秘伝のガマ油じゃ。
It's the secret toad oil
of Mount Myoboku.
ガマ油？
Toad oil?
ちょっと こっちへ来て
片手出してみ。
Come over here and
put out your hand.
ん？
ほい。
Here.
このガマ油は
自然エネルギーを引き寄せる力がある。
This toad oil has the property
of attracting Nature Energy.
修業の手助けをするものじゃ。
It helps with the training.
アハハ 便利なのあんじゃん。
Hey, that's useful!
この油を体に塗りつければ➡
Whenever you rub this oil
on your body,
そこから自然エネルギーが
体に入ってくるんじゃ。
Nature Energy can enter
through there.
そうすれば だんだんと➡
And gradually, you'll gain the ability
to sense Nature Energy.
自然エネルギーを
肌で感じるようになる。
確かに
なんか 肌で感じる気がする。
You're right...
I think I feel something
through my skin.
これは 感覚をつかむきっかけを
つくるものじゃ。
It is a tool to help grasp
the concept.
いずれは 油がなくても
できるようになってくるが➡
In time, you won't even need
to use the oil.
ただし リスクもある。
However, there is a risk.
えっ!?
自然エネルギーコントロールが
未熟な者に使うと➡
When used by one who is inexperienced
in controlling Nature Energy,
カエルになっていくんじゃ。
you start to turn into a frog.
いぃ!?
えぇ～!?
な な なんだ これ？
Wh-Wh-What the hell is this?!
ああ 助けて！
カエルやだ！ ぎゃあ～!!
Help!
I don't wanna be a frog!
イッテ… 何すんだ。
Oww!
What's the big idea?
戻った。
I'm back to normal.
(フカサク)すべては バランスじゃ。
It's all about balance.
精神エネルギーと身体エネルギーは
忍術チャクラで練り慣れとるから➡
You're used to turning your Mental
and Physical Energy
into ninjutsu chakra,
バランスは取れるだろうがのう。
so you've got a balance there.
そこに 外からの自然エネルギーも➡
But now, you must add
Nature Energy into the mix.
バランスよく練りこむのは
至難の業じゃ。
Getting the perfect balance
is extremely difficult.
バランスか。
Balance, huh?
少なすぎれば
仙術チャクラはできん。
PHYSICAL     MENTAL    NATURE
Take in too little, and you won't
get Sage Jutsu chakra.
かといって 多すぎれば
自然エネルギーに取り込まれて➡
And yet, if you take in too much,
Nature Energy will overwhelm you
and turn you into a frog.
カエルになってしまう。
多少 取り込みすぎたくらいなら
元に戻すこともできるがのう。
Of course, if you only take in
a little too much, it's reversible.
自然エネルギーを
大幅に取り込みすぎたら➡
But get beyond a certain amount,
and you'll stay as a frog,
カエルになったまま
二度と 元には戻れんようになる。
never reverting back to
a human again.
さっき 死ぬっつったのは➡
What I meant about you
having to die
人として死ぬかもしれん
つうことじゃい。
is that you might stop being human.
カエルになった者は➡
Once you turn into a frog,
更に自然の一部に
なってしまうのじゃ。
then you progress further toward
permanently becoming one with nature.
かつて 修業に失敗した者たちの
なれの果てが➡
And the past students
who've failed in this training...
この石像たちじゃ。
are those stone statues.
これ 全部…。
All of them?
まあ 少しは安心せい。
Well, don't fret too much.
わしがついとるし➡
You have me.
このハタキ棒は 自然エネルギーを
外へ叩き出すものじゃ。
And this baton beats Nature Energy
out of one's body.
ナルトちゃんが
カエルに変化していくようなら➡
If you start transforming into a frog,
わしが これで
逐一 叩き直してやるけんのう。
I'll beat you thoroughly to reverse it.
はっきり言うとじゃ。
Speaking truthfully,
あの自来也ちゃんですら
完璧には こなせんかった。
even Jiraiya-boy wasn't able
to completely master this.
自来也ちゃんは
仙術チャクラを練ると➡
When molding Sage Jutsu chakra,
少しカエルに化けてしもうとった。
Jiraiya-boy always acquired
some frog features.
それでも
うまく練り込めたほうじゃ。
But he was among the skilled ones.
ここまできて
臆することもなかろうが➡
I doubt that you'd hesitate
after coming this far,
一応 聞いておく。
but let me ask you...
どうする？
What will you do?
やる。
I'll do it!
オレの忍道は エロ仙人と同じだ。
My Ninja Way...
is the same as the Pervy Sage's!
The First Challenge
(マダラ)やっと六尾も揃ったか。
We finally got the Six-Tails.
(ペイン)これで すぐにでも
九尾を狩りにいける。
Now we can go on the hunt
for the Nine-Tails.
(マダラ)それがいい。
自来也をやったことで➡
Good idea.
Because you killed Jiraiya,
the Leaf will set their eyes on you.
木ノ葉は
お前に目をつけたはずだ。
時間が経てば経つほど➡
The more time passes,
向こうも
何かしらの手を考えてくる。
the more likely they'll set
some plan in motion.
やりにくくなる前に動け。
Take action before it becomes
more difficult.
(小南)ペインは無敵…。
どんなことがあっても➡
Pain is invincible...
No matter what happens,
we will capture the Nine-Tails.
九尾は確実に手に入れる。
尾獣は あと一匹。
There's just one more Tailed Beast left.
あと二匹では？
Not two?
Sasuke has already captured
the Eight-Tails.
すでに 八尾は
サスケが狩った。
I see.
なるほど。
小南 すぐに準備しろ。
Konan, make preparations immediately.
これから 木ノ葉へ向かう。
We're heading out to the Hidden Leaf.
Oww!
イテッ！
明日は 体中
超内出血だってばよ！
Tomorrow, I'm going to be bruised
and bleeding on the inside.
なんじゃ もうギブアップかいな。
What? Giving up already?
あのさ もっと要領のいい
修業法があるんだってばよ。
Hey, I know a much better
training method.
なんじゃそりゃ？
影分身を使った修業法だ。
What is it?
Use Shadow Clones for the training.
そうすりゃ 経験値が
何倍にもなるんだから。
They exponentially increase
my progress!
なるほどの。
You have a point.
The experience of the Shadow Clones
reverts back to the original.
影分身の感覚は
オリジナルに還元されるからのう。
しかしじゃ 逆に言うなら➡
But the reverse is also true...
If a Shadow Clone completely
changes into a frog,
影分身が
完全にカエルになってしもうたら➡
オリジナルのほうも終わりじゃぞ！
it's over for the original.
I know that already.
んなことは わかってるよ！
よかろう。
Very well. But four is the limit!
４人までじゃ。 それ以上は
わしのハタキ棒が間に合わん！
Any more and neither the baton
or I can keep up!
All right!
よっしゃ！
イテッ！
イタッ！
おっ！
イテッ！
We're not playing a game
of whack-a-mole!
もぐらたたきゲーム
やっとるんじゃねえんじゃぞ！
修業じゃ！
これじゃ わしがもたん。
This is training!
I'm not gonna last doing this!
Damn!
クソッ！
イテッ！
Oww!
これは 叩かれて
こんな顔になったんだってばよ！
My face is like this from being hit!
カエルになったんじゃねえって！
I'm not turning into a frog!
What?! Sorry.
なんじゃと… すまん。
自然エネルギーを感じるだけの修業が➡
I never thought that training
to feel Nature Energy
こんなに難しいとは思わなかった。
would be so hard.
つらい修業に耐えてこそ
本当の力が手に入るのじゃ。
Only through perseverance shall
true strength be gained.
それは わかってるよ！
I know that!
エロ仙人みてぇに強くなれんなら
誰だって我慢するってもんだ。
If it'll make me strong like
the Pervy Sage,
anyone would endure this.
いや それはムリじゃ。
え？
No... That's impossible.
この修業は 誰もが
できるというわけではない。
This training is not for everyone...
ナルトちゃんと
自来也ちゃんだからこそのもの。
You could say it's only possible
because it's you and Jiraiya-boy.
そう言っても ええ。
じゃなきゃ ここへは連れてこん。
Or else I wouldn't have even
brought you here.
どういうことだってばよ？
What do you mean?
己の内に膨大なチャクラを持つ者。
Unless you already possess
enormous chakra inside you,
でなけりゃ たちまち自然エネルギーに
取り込まれてしまうけんの。
Nature Energy would just take
over you right away.
それだけ
自然エネルギーはすごいのじゃ。
That is how intense Nature Energy is.
はあ…。
Plus, they must have the guts
to never give up.
その上
あきらめん ド根性のある者。
それが 仙人になれる人間じゃ。
That's the kind of person who
can become a Sage.
All right! Let's do this then!
よっしゃ！ やったるで！
アホ!! 死ぬ気か！
Fool! Do you want to kill yourself?!
見えた！ やった！
I can see it!
- Yes!
- It seems he's starting
《どうやら
少しは 自然エネルギーを➡
- I can see it! I can see it!
- to get the feel of Nature Energy.
感じ取れるように
なってきたようじゃな》
フサカク様
そろそろ 腹減ってきたのう。
- Lord Fukasaku, I'm getting a little hungry.
- I saw it! I saw it!
そうじゃな。 ナルトちゃん
少し休憩じゃ！ 弁当にする。
- You're right.
- I saw it!
- Naruto-boy, time for a break.
- I'm awesome, yeah!
Let's eat.
Eat up now.
(フカサク)たんと食うとけよ。
(フカサク)休憩が終わったら 仙術で
岩蛙を持ち上げてみるけんの。
After the break,
I'll have you try to lift up
the stone frogs using Sage Jutsu.
お… おっす！
Y-Yes sir!
うまいじゃろ
かあちゃんの特製じゃけんの。
Good, huh?
They're Ma's special dishes.
どれも オレの大好物じゃ！
They're all favorites of mine.
《意外とうまく感じた。
That actually tasted quite good.
やっぱり 人間から離れてる…》
I'm becoming less human, after all.
さて 岩蛙を
持ち上げるわけじゃが➡
Now then, I want you to
raise the stone frog.
まずは 己の忍術チャクラだけで
持ち上げてみんさい。
But first, try it using only
your ninjutsu chakra.
うん！
O-Okay.
よし！
All right!
んっ！ うぅ…。
I can't lift it!
上がらねえ！
はい やめ！
All right, stop!
だぁ～！ ハァ ハァ…。
じゃあ 仙術チャクラを練ってみ！
Now, mold some Sage Jutsu chakra!
おっす！
Right!
よし！
もう一度 岩蛙やってみい！
Good! Now try lifting
the stone frog once more!
うん！
Okay!
おっ！
Oh!
That's it! Naruto-boy!
いいぞ！ ナルトちゃん！
うぅっ!!
おりゃっ!!
やるがな ナルト！
Nice, Naruto!
《自来也ちゃんのときより
のみこみが早いのう この子は》
This lad's quicker on
the uptake than Jiraiya-boy.
やったぁ！
アホッ！
I did it!
Fool! How dare you treat your predecessor
with such disrespect!
先人を粗末に扱うなや！
あぁ～!!
《マヌケなのも
自来也ちゃん以上じゃが…》
Though he's a lot denser
than Jiraiya-boy too...
よし！ ナルトちゃん。
All right, Naruto-boy!
倒れた全部の岩を
元に戻すんじゃ！
Now put all the toppled stones
back in place!
マジか～！
Are you serious?!
(ゼツ)八尾か…。
The Eight-Tails, huh?
サスケは うまくやったようだな。
It seems Sasuke was successful.
(マダラ)九尾は ペインが持ってくる。
Pain will bring the Nine-Tails.
(フカサク)どうやら 油を使うコントロールを
マスターしたようじゃな。
It appears you've mastered
toad oil assisted control.
次は 油を使わずに➡
Now you need to master
controlling Nature Energy
自然エネルギーの
コントロールをする修業じゃ。
without using the oil.
力が みなぎってくる！
I can feel the power flowing into me!
体内エネルギーだけを消費していく
忍術チャクラは➡
Ninjutsu chakra consumes
your internal energy.
使えば使うほど 疲れていくがな。
The more you use it,
the more exhausted you will become.
仙術チャクラは それと違って➡
In contrast, Sage Jutsu chakra
draws in external energy,
外から エネルギーを取り入れるけん。
so it will not tire you.
疲れるどころか回復も早いんじゃ。
In fact, you will recover and
heal quicker too.
そっか。
I get it...
《まっ 九尾のチャクラとあいまって
異常な回復をみせとるがのう》
Well... With the Nine-Tails' chakra
in the mix too,
he's showing a truly remarkable
recovery rate.
これなら
あれが できるかもしれねえ。
Now maybe I can do that too...
なんじゃ？
あっ！ いや その…。
Do what?
Huh?! Oh, nothing...
なんでもねえってばよ。
まあ ええ。
Nothing at all!
Never mind then... But here.
それより これじゃ。
今日はこれを ナルトちゃんに
渡そうと思ったんじゃ。
I thought I'd give you
this today, Naruto-boy.
ん？ 何？
What is it?
本じゃ。
本？
A book.
Book?
これは 自来也ちゃんが
最初に書いた小説じゃ。
This is the first novel
Jiraiya-boy wrote.
ここには 自来也ちゃんの
思いが込められておる。
A lot of Jiraiya-boy's mind and
heart are contained within it.
読むとええ。
You should read it.
『ド根性忍伝』…。
TALES OF A GUTSY NINJA
Tales of...a Gutsy Ninja.
そろそろ観念したらどうだ？
Why don't you give it up?
鬼ごっこも
そろそろ飽きてきたぜ。
This game of tag is getting boring.
あきらめろ。
Give it up.
ひと言 いいか？
Can I say one thing?
聞く気はねえ！
I don't care to listen!
もう くたばれ！
Die already!
オレが あきらめるのを…。
Give up...
あきらめろ！
on me giving up!
オ… オレを倒しても➡
Even if you bring me down,
また次の刺客が この里を襲う。
another assassin will attack
the village...
ヘヘヘ…
オレたちが呪われた忍の世界に➡
As long as we are cursed to
live in this Ninja World,
生きているかぎり平穏は… ない。
there will be no peace.
なら…。
オレが その呪いを解いてやる。
Then...I'll break that curse!
平和ってものが もしあるなら
オレがそれを つかみとってやる。
If there is such a thing as peace,
I'll seize it!
オレは あきらめない！
I'll never give up!
キ… キサマは…。
Wh-Who are you...?
オレの名は…。
My name is...
TALES OF A GUTSY NINJA
JIRAIYA
((サスケは
オレとの繋がりを断ち切って➡
Sasuke said he was going to
sever his bond with me
強くなるって言ってた。
and become stronger.
お前なんかに
オレの気持は わからないって。
He said I could never understand
his feelings.
エロ仙人と大蛇丸も
昔 友達だったんだろう？
You were friends with Orochimaru
long ago, right, Pervy Sage?
どうして大蛇丸は 里を抜けて➡
Why did Orochimaru desert
the village
木ノ葉崩しなんか
したんだってばよ？
and decide to destroy the Hidden Leaf?
大蛇丸が
おかしくなってきたのは➡
Orochimaru changed after
his parents were killed.
両親を殺されてからだ。
それからは
禁術に とりつかれていった。
He became obsessed with
the Forbidden Jutsu.
両親に会いたかったのか…。
Maybe he longed to see his parents...
それとも 両親を死に追いやった
木ノ葉への復讐か…。
Or he sought revenge
on the Leaf Village,
who he held responsible
for their deaths.
わしは
親を殺されては おらんからのう。
My parents weren't killed.
わしも お前と同じだ。
So like you,
アイツに 何もわかってないと
一喝されてのう。
I was accused of not being
able to understand.
そのとおり アイツのことを➡
Perhaps he was right,
何もわかってやれんかったの
かもしれん。
and I didn't understand a thing about him...
だがのう…。
However...
こんな わしでも➡
Even I can see there's too much hate
in our Ninja World.
この忍の世に 憎しみが
はびこっているのは わかる。
憎しみ…。
Hate?
その憎しみを どうにかしたいとは
思っとるんだが➡
And I've wanted to do something
about this hatred,
どうしたらいいのか
わしにも まだわからん。
yet I'm not sure what must be done.
だが いつかは➡
But I have faith...
人が 本当の意味で
理解しあえる時代が来ると➡
that there will come a time
when people can truly understand
one another.
わしは信じとる。
なんか 難しいってばよ。
It all sounds kinda complicated.
答えが見つからんかったときは➡
And if I can't find the answer,
その答えを
お前に託すとしようかのう。
perhaps I will entrust you to find it.
オッス！ エロ仙人の頼みなら
しかたねえってばよ！
Yes, sir! I can't turn you down,
can I, Pervy Sage?
何？ なんで笑うんだってばよ。
What? Why are you laughing?
お前の笑顔には救われるようじゃ。
Your smile is my salvation.
お前を弟子にして よかったわい。
I'm glad I made you my student.
そっかぁ？
R-Really?
だが… わしも
まだ あきらめたわけじゃない。
But I haven't given up yet.
わしは 自分の書いた本で
この世を変えるつもりじゃ。
PRODUCTION NOTEBOOK
I plan to change this world
with my books!
売れない その本で？
With those books that don't sell?
愚か者！ そのうち バカ売れじゃ！
You fool!
They'll be bestsellers before
you know it!
そのときになって
サインをねだっても➡
And when that day finally arrives,
お前にゃ書いてやらんからのう！
I won't autograph your copies
even if you beg me!
(いらねえってばよ そんなの！))
I don't need any of that!
いらねえってばよ…。
I don't need any of that...
《エロ仙人には➡
'Cuz Pervy Sage... You gave me
something much more valuable.
もっと大切なもん
もらってっからよ》
こう 人数が少ないと
時間が かかるね。
With so few people,
it sure is taking a while.
うるさい！ 黙って集中しろ。
Shut up!
Be quiet and focus.
(鬼鮫)サスケ君…
どうやら ヘマしたようですね。
It appears...
Sasuke has blundered.
ハハハハ… タコの足だ！
An octopus leg!
笑うな！
Quit laughing!
ハハハハッ！
What's this sensation?
(アルザック)ここにいたのか。
(ビスカ)アル…。
I don't feel uncomfortable
being still at all!
(アルザック)何を読んでるんだい？
(ビスカ)『星空の鍵』よ。
Is this what it feels like to become
one with nature?
ああ… ギルドでもサポートしようって➡
I'm not using the toad oil,
but I can tell power is being gathered
from everywhere!
大聖堂の書庫から
借りてきたんだったな。
I can feel the power surging
inside of me!
(アスカ)あれ～？
ん？
この本 これで終わり？
Is this Sage Mode?!
そうよ。
(アルザック)どうかしたのかい？
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"Surpassing the Master"
(アスカ)う～ん。